翻译：脸盆王子  牛奶器  小蛮腰
校对：苏小黛
总监：somehacker
后期：Sung
如果你有发烧  咳嗽  喉咙痛等症状
If you have a fever and cough or sore throat.
请留在家中
Stay home.
要我说这有95%的可能是实验室搞出来的
I'd say 95% chance this is manufactured came out of a laboratory.
病源可追溯到
The source of the virus was traced back to
在旧金山创维实验室所做的药物检测
drug testing done at gen-sys laboratories in San Francisco.
目前认定的首位感染者是实验室技术人员
The lab technician now known as patient zero
他意外接触到了ALZ-113逆转录酶病毒
was accidentally exposed to retrovirus alz-113,
这是种针对阿兹海默症的试用药物
an Alzheimer's trial drug
当时正用黑猩猩来做试验
that was being tested on chimpanzees.
受到感染的黑猩猩
The infected chimps
表现出了不稳定性并伴有攻击行为
showed signs of erratic and aggressive behavior
最终导致它们逃离了实验室
that led to their escape from the facility.
金门大桥上的事件现在已经众所周知
The now-famous incident on the golden gate bridge.
黑猩猩与警方对峙了6小时
A six-hour standoff with police.
最终消失在了红木森林中
Ended with the apes disappearing into muir woods.
急诊室已经不堪重负
Emergency rooms are being overwhelmed with
挤满了出现"猿流感"征兆的患者
patients showing signs of what's being dubbed "The simian flu."
疾病控制中心预测
The CDC is projecting a fatality toll
未来六到八个月
ranging from 5 million
死亡人数将从五百万增至一亿五千万
to as many as 150 million in the next 6 to 8 months.
出现感染症状的人都会得到特殊治疗
Anyone showing signs of a contagious illness will receive special treatment here.
机场已专门建立了检疫中心
The airport's purpose-built quarantine center.
许多新来者
Many of the new arrivals are
都是与父母失去联系的孩子
children who have lost contact with their parents.
强制隔离措施引发了国内骚乱
The mandatory quarantines have sparked civil unrest.
很多家庭因此被拆散
Families are being ripped apart.
隔离不太可能有效
Containment is not very likely.
跟你的家人做好准备  熟悉逃生路线
Prepare your families. Know your evacuation route.
目前的存活率约为五百分之一
The survival rate is now approximately 1 in 500.
今晚在市中心发生了暴力冲突
Violence erupted in the city center tonight.
这已是这些天的来第三起暴力事件
The third incident in as many days.
已有28个国家宣布进入戒严状态
Martial law has been declared in 28 nations,
包括美国和加拿大
including the U.S. And Canada.
核反应堆过热  我们阻止不了它熔毁
The reactor is overheating. We can't stop a meltdown.
民众秩序完全陷入了混乱
Just a total collapse of anything resembling civilian order.
由于猿流感肆虐成风
Due to the extremity of the simian flu crisis,
所有的政府职能部门都已无限期关闭
all regular government functions have been suspended indefinitely.
那些没被病毒杀死的人
Those who aren't killed by the virus,
也许会死在斗争中
will probably die in the fighting.
也许就这样了
So, maybe this is it.
这就是结束
This is how it ends.
很快
Pretty soon,
人类就会灭绝了
there won't be anyone left.
猩球崛起2:黎明之战
凯撒
Caesar.
它们在靠近
They are close.
科巴
Koba!
现在动手吗  父亲
Now, father?
儿子  别动
Son, stay.
谢谢  科巴
Thank you, koba.
儿子  要三思而后行
Think before you act, son.
别不开心了  蓝瞳
Don't feel bad, Blue Eyes.
受伤能让你变得更强
Scars make you strong.
过来看看你的弟弟
Come meet your new brother.
又一个儿子
Another son.
不禁感叹我们已经走多久了  莫里斯
Makes me think how far we've come, Maurice.
貌似很久了
Seems long ago.
还会想他们吗
Still think about them?
人类吗
Humans?
有时候会
Sometimes.
我没有像你那样了解过他们
Didn't know them like you did.
我只看到他们坏的一面
Only saw their bad side.
好的  坏的  现在都不重要了
Good, bad. doesn't matter now.
人类自己毁灭了自己
Humans destroyed each other.
咱们也会打架啊
Apes fight too.
但咱们是一家人
But we are family.
真想知道他们是不是真的都不在了
Wonder if they're really all gone.
都过了10个冬天了
Ten winters now.
上两个冬天就不见他们的踪迹了
Last two, no sign of them.
他们肯定都不在了
They must be gone.
蓝瞳  换我就不会被那熊伤到  我多快啊
That bear wouldn't get me, blue eyes. I'm quick!
闭嘴  嘘
Shut up, ash!
天啊
Oh, God.
没事的
It's okay.
没事的  没事的
It's okay. It's okay.
别动
Freeze!
Stay!
帮忙
Help!
快来帮忙
不许动
No!
在这里
Over here!
我打中他了  我打中他了
I shot him! I shot him.
他们打中了灰灰  他们打了我儿子
They shot ash! Shot my son!
火箭  先等等
Rocket, wait.
我们无意伤害你们
We don't mean any harm!
他们可是猩猩  怎么会听懂你说什么
They're apes, man. You think they understand what you're saying?
你觉得他们只是普通猩猩吗
Do they look like just apes to you?
爸爸
Dad.
马尔科姆  你干什么
Malcolm, what are you doing?
-爸爸  -马尔科姆
- Dad? - Malcolm.
没事
It's okay.
把枪放下
Put your guns down.
-说什么呢  -放下
- You can't be serious. - Do it.
滚
Go!
天啊
Holy shit.
好的  我们马上走
Okay. Okay, we're going.
滚
Go!
-慢点  -快走  走
- Slowly. - Go, go, go!
我的包
My bag!
快走
Go!
科巴
Koba!
跟着他们
Follow!
找到了吗
Did you find it?
我们得谈谈
We need to talk.
怎么了  什么事
What? What's wrong?
水坝几乎是完好的
The dam is pretty much intact.
估计一周内就能开始为我们提供能源
It could probably start generating power for us within a week.
但有个问题  上车再说
But there is a problem. Get in.
我打中他了
I shot him.
我很害怕  不知道该怎么做
I was scared. I didn't know what to do.
天啊  那里有多少只
Jesus Christ. How many were there?
很多  大概80只
A lot. Like, 80.
-至少80只  -好了
- At least. - Okay.
你都没听到他说什么  他们会说话
You're not hearing what he's saying. They spoke!
这不可能
That is not possible.
我跟你说  德雷福斯
I'm telling you, Dreyfus,
他们确实会说话  非常惊人
they did and it was incredible.
惊人  他们是会说话的猩猩
Incredible? They're talking apes!
-还他妈带着长矛  -得了
- With big-ass Spears! - Please!
我不知道你认为自己看见或听到了什么
I don't know exactly what you think you saw or heard,
但你得给我安静下来  好吗
but you have to calm down, okay?
病毒方面呢  埃莉  有任何进展吗
What about the virus, Ellie? Any chance of contagion?
我们是因为基因免疫
We're all genetically immune,
不然早就死了
or we would've been dead a long time ago.
这你可不能确定
You don't know that for sure.
她是疾控中心的  她怎么不确定
She worked with the CDC. She knows.
我们怎么办
What are we gonna do?
我不知道
I don't know.
我们需要那里的能源
We need that power.
他本可以杀死我们  但他没有
He could've killed us, but he didn't.
也许他故意留我们小命  好跟踪我们
Maybe he kept us alive, so they could follow us.
找到我们所在  再一举杀光
They find out where we are, and they kill us all!
"他"是指谁
What do you mean, "He"?
这就是我们想告诉你的
That's what we're trying to tell you.
你绝对前所未见
It was unlike anything you've ever seen before,
他们的首领
and the leader...
绝对非同寻常
He was remarkable.
是吗
Really?
-你是这么想的吗  -这是我们看到的
- Is that what you thought? - It's what we saw.
没错  我们都看到的
Yeah, it's what we all saw.
回去不能再提及此事  懂吗
Not a word of this back at the colony, you understand me?
在没想出办法前一句话也不能提
Not a word until we can figure out what to do.
-开什么玩笑  -我不是在开玩笑
- You gotta be kidding. - No, I'm not kidding.
我不想制造恐慌
I don't want to create a panic.
怎么样  伙计  你还好吧
How are you doing, pal? Are you okay?
-我的包掉了  -我知道
- I dropped my bag. - I know.
-你的写生本也在里边吗  -没了
- Was your sketchbook in there? - It's gone.
卡弗刚跟我说
Carver just told me
不能跟任何人提起那里发生了什么
we're not gonna tell anybody what happened up there.
暂时先别说
Not yet. No.
我们必须现在就打过去
Must attack them now!
以防他们先动手
Before they attack us!
我们不知道他们有多少人
We don't know how many there are.
有多少枪
How many guns they have?
也不知道他们来这里干什么
Or why they came up here?
他们开枪打了你儿子  火箭
They shot your son, Rocket!
难道你不想报仇吗
Don't you want to fight?
我听凯撒的
I follow Caesar.
科巴说得没错
Koba's right!
他们差点杀了你  灰灰
They almost killed you, ash!
不
No!
如果挑起战争
If we go to war,
我们可能会失去这些年来建立的
we could lose all we've built...
家园
Home.
家人
Family.
未来
Future.
明早之前我会作出决定
I will decide by morning.
凯撒
Caesar.
多年来我一直被人类囚禁在实验室
For years I was a prisoner in their lab.
他们拿我开刀
They cut me,
不断地折磨我
tortured me.
是你救了我
You freed me.
我可以为你做任何事
I would do anything you ask.
但我们必须展示实力
But we must show strength!
我们会的  科巴
We will, koba.
借过  借过
Coming through. Coming through.
这他妈可远不只80啊
That's a hell of a lot more than eighty!
马尔科姆
Malcolm!
猿族
Apes
不想要战争
do not want war.
但若有必要
But will fight,
我们定将战斗
if we must.
猿族的家
Ape home.
人类的家
Human home.
不要再过来
Do not come back.
各位
Everyone!
各位  你们得冷静
Everyone, you have to calm down!
各位
Everybody.
所有人
Everybody!
请冷静  我们都是免疫的
Please! We're all immune!
我们都免疫  不然也不会站在这里
We're all immune, or we wouldn't still be here!
他们怎么找到这的
How did they find us?
是我们先找到他们的
We found them.
你知道他们在哪里
You knew they were out there!
万一他们回来怎么办
What if they come back?
要是他们回来
If they come back, if they come back,
他们一定会后悔
they'll be sorry they ever did!
尽管现在这座城市的人口不复当年
Now, this city may not have the manpower it once did.
但它还拥有火力
But it has the firepower.
身后那批武器弹药
Those stockpiles left behind.
联邦应急管理局的  国民警卫队的
By fema, the national guard,
现在都归我们了
we have it all.
听着
Look,
我知道你们为什么害怕
I know why you're scared.
相信我  我也害怕
I'm scared, too, believe me.
但我知道自己身上背负着你们的信任
But I recognize the trust you've all placed in me.
我们一起闯过鬼门关
We've been through hell together.
你们也都知道现在我们面临着什么
But you all know what we're up against.
燃料快用完了
We're almost out of fuel.
这意味着提供不了电力
Which means no more power.
意味着我们要过回以前的苦日子
Which means we could slip back to the way things were.
而那边的水坝就是解决方案
That dam up there was the answer.
只是我们没想到他们也在那边
We just had no idea they were up there, too.
那现在该怎么办
So, what do we do now?
是啊
Yeah!
我们会想别的办法
We find another way.
因为那里的电力
Because that power
不仅仅能使灯泡发光
is not just about keeping the lights on.
还能为我们提供工具
It's about giving us the tools,
与外面的世界重新取得联系
to reconnect to the rest of the world,
找到外面的同伴
To find out who else is out there.
这样我们就能开始重建
So that we can start to rebuild,
并且再造
and reclaim,
我们失去的世界
the world we lost.
讲得不错
That was a great speech.
但根本就没有可替代的能源
There is no alternative power source.
水坝是我们的唯一选择
That dam is the only option.
那只能跟他们拼了
Well, then, we fight them.
还有两周燃料就用完了
We're two weeks away from running out of fuel.
最多能撑三周
Maybe three, tops.
我知道
I know.
燃料一旦用完
And once that happens,
我就不能再拿着个扩音器上去
I won't be able to go out there with a bullhorn,
指望他们平静下来了
and calm everybody down.
我们需要电力让无线电发射机重新运作
We need that power to get the radio transmitter working.
这是与外界取得联系的唯一办法
It's our only chance of reaching the outside world.
我们得找到其他幸存者
We have to find other survivors.
是啊  幸存者不多了
Yeah. There's not that many of us left.
不能再有人牺牲了
We can't afford any more casualties.
是我们找到了这个地方
We founded this place.
-我跟你  -我知道
- You and I. - I know.
靠能源才能让我们回到从前的日子
On the idea that power would lead us back to the life we once had.
要是我们不团结  也许就活不下来了
If we can't stick together, maybe we can't survive.
我失去了一切
I lost everything.
一想到会再失去身边仅有的...
The idea of losing what little I have is...
我想回到那里去
I want to go back up there.
听我说  给我三天时间
Listen to me. Give me three days.
让我跟他谈
Let me talk to him.
行不通的话  再按你说的做
If it doesn't work, then we do it your way.
万一适得其反  万一他暴怒了呢
And what if it backfires? What if he gets violent?
你怎么知道他能明白你
I mean, how do you know that he'll even understand you?
他不仅仅是只黑猩猩
He's more than just an ape.
我要带些人到尖兵堡
I'm gonna take some men up to fort point.
去军械库找找看
I'm gonna go through the armory.
看哪些还能用的
I'm gonna see what's still working.
三天
Three days.
要是你三天还没回来
You're not back in three days,
我们就冲上去
we're going up there,
把他们杀到一只不剩
and we're gonna kill every last one of them.
卡弗正在备车
Carver is getting the trucks ready.
他跟福斯特还有肯普马上就到
He'll be here with Foster and Kemp any minute.
真的要带上卡弗吗
You're really taking carver?
他可开枪打了他们
I mean, he shot one of them.
我也没办法
I don't really have any choice.
他在水利部门工作过
He used to work at the water department.
只有他知道怎么让水坝运作起来
He's the only one who knows how the dam works.
马尔科姆
Malcolm.
你去了打算怎么做  打算说什么
What are you gonna do up there? What are you gonna say?
我会跟他说实话
I'll tell him the truth.
希望赶上他心情好
Hope I catch him in a good mood.
你一定觉得我疯了
You think I'm crazy.
我是担心
I'm worried.
是啊  我也是
Yeah, so am I.
我仔细想了一遍
I've gone over it in my head,
要是我连试都不试
and I think if I don't at least try this,
那战争就真的无法避免了
there's gonna be a war.
把我也带上
Take me with you.
有人受伤怎么办  我可以帮忙
What if someone gets hurt? You'll need me there.
我爱你
I love you.
但我需要你留在这里
But I need you to stay here.
我不想留下亚历山大一个人
I don't want Alexander to be alone.
我也去
I'm coming, too.
儿子  那里不安全
Son, it's not safe.
待在你身边总比在这里安全
But I'm safer with you than I am down here.
我也去
I'm coming.
求你了
Please.
任何人都不许离开这辆车
No one gets out of the trucks.
任何人
No one.
要是我两个小时还没回来
If I'm not back in two hours,
你就带他们回城
you get everyone back to the city.
不会有事的
It's gonna be okay.
拜托  拜托
Please. Please. Please.
请别杀我
Please don't kill me.
先听我说
Just hear what I have to say.
我知道
I know.
"不要再回来"  我知道
"Don't come back." I know.
我来这里是因为...
I wouldn't be here unless it were...
好吧  好吧  好吧
Okay! Okay! Okay!
好  好  好
Okay, okay, okay.
我得带你去一个地方
I need to show you something.
离这不远
It's not far.
人类在撒谎
Human lies!
不  不
No! No!
不  不  不  我发誓
No, no, no. I swear.
去了你就明白了
If I could just show you, then you'll understand.
拜托了
Please.
带路
Show me.
这就是人类所谓的"小型水电站"
This is what we used to call a "Small hydro".
本来是为这里以北的区域供电的
It was built to service areas to the north of here.
我们在试着把线路改装向城市供电
But we've been working to reroute the power lines to the city.
城里核电站的能源
Because the city used to run off nuclear power,
几年前就告竭了
but that ran out years ago.
这些年一直靠柴油发电机和气化炉度日
So, we've been using diesel generators and gasifiers.
但要是能让这个水坝重新发电
But if we can just get this dam working,
就可以将有限的化石能源贮存起来
then we have a shot at restoring limited power.
你能明白我的意思吗
Is any of this making any sense to you?
灯光
The... lights.
是的
Yes.
灯光
The lights.
这是你的家园
This is your home.
我从没想过将它夺走  真的
And I don't want to take it away from you, I promise.
但如果你允许我们在这里施工
But if you can allow us, let us do our work here...
你还带了别人
You brought others?
就几个人
Just a few.
我不会造成任何威胁
I'm not a threat.
不然的话
If I am,
你随时可以杀了我
then I guess you can kill me.
不是吧
Come on!
等等  别慌  别慌
Wait, wait, wait! Stop, stop.
我们得把枪给他们
We need to give them our guns.
就这一个条件
That's the one condition.
什么意思
What does that mean?
我们能留下了
We can stay.
人类有了电力就会变得更危险
If they get power, they'll be more dangerous!
为什么要帮他们
Why help them?!
他们似乎已经走投无路了
They seem desperate.
如果赶走他们  以后一定会强攻过来
If we make them go, they'll attack.
来就来
Let them.
趁其疲弱  一举消灭他们
We'll destroy them while they're weak.
有多少猿类得为此牺牲
And how many apes will die?
这是一个缔造和平的机会
We have one chance for peace.
让人类干完他们的活  他们就会离开
Let them do their human work. Then they'll go.
人类干的活
Human work?
Human work.
人类干的活
Human work!
科巴说
Koba say,
猿族应该憎恨人类
apes should hate humans...
够了
Enough!
科巴在人类身上
From humans Koba learned hate,
只学到了仇恨
but nothing else.
你得吃点东西
Hey, you need to eat.
好  我只是
Okay, I just...
今天你的所作所为十分勇敢
That was brave, what you did today.
马尔科姆
Malcolm.
我知道现在所有人都指望着你
I know everyone's depending on you...
我才不在乎  我一点也不在乎
I don't care about that. I don't care about any of that.
我只在乎他
I care about him.
他经历的都不是小孩应该经历的事
He saw things that no kid should see,
我不会让情况再次恶化了
and I'm not letting us go back to that.
我知道
I know.
我也在试着消除和他的隔阂
I have been trying to get closer to him.
但
But...
总有一天会的
You will.
知道猿类可怕在哪儿吗
You know the scary thing about them?
他们不需要电力  灯光
They don't need power, lights.
暖气  什么都不需要
Heat. Nothing.
伙计
Hey, pal.
那是猿类的优势
That's their advantage.
是他们比人类强大的原因
That's what makes them stronger.
马尔科姆  今晚应该留一个人守夜
Malcolm, I'm thinking one of us should stand guard tonight.
拿什么守  枪都被缴了
With what? They took our guns.
他们要真动了杀心  咱们根本活不到现在
If they wanted us dead, we would be dead already.
他们可能只是不着急动手
Maybe they're just taking their time.
都已经干掉地球上一半的人了
They killed off half the planet already.
拜托
Come on.
怎么
What?
这真不能怪猿类
You can't honestly blame the apes.
那怪谁  本来就是猿流感
Who the hell else am I going to blame? It was the simian flu.
那也是实验室里科学家创造出来的病毒
It was a virus created by scientists in a lab.
猩猩只是无辜的试验对象
The chimps they were testing on didn't have a say in the matter.
别跟我扯大道理
Spare me the hippie-dippie bullshit.
你敢说你看到他们时
You're telling me you don't get sick to your stomach
不觉得恶心吗
at the sight of them?
你以前不还有个女儿吗
Didn't you have a little girl?
卡弗  够了
Carver, that's enough.
-她是怎么死的  -够了
- How did she die? - That's enough!
你老婆也是
Or your wife, for that matter.
卡弗  再不闭嘴我就要揍人了
Carver, you better shut up before I kick your ass.
好吧
Okay.
算我嘴贱
I'm the asshole.
没事吧
Are you okay?
你听起来生病了  还好吗
You sound sick... you OK?
只是需要休息
Just need rest.
你操心人类的事就好
You worry about the humans.
科巴哪儿去了
Where's Koba?
生闷气呢
Still angry.
他说要去打猎
Said he was going hunting.
看  下面有人类
Look, humans below!
我们来这干什么
Why are we here?
凯撒相信人类
Caesar trusts humans.
科巴可不信
Koba does not.
大多数武器应该还能用
Most of the arsenal seems functional.
好的
Good.
我们安排了人在那边试射
We're testing them out back.
别动
Don't you move!
叫你别动  懂吗
Don't move, do you understand me?
特里
Terry!
特里  快过来
Terry, get in here, quick!
我操
Holy shit.
怎么办  怎么办
What do we do? What do we do?
他从哪儿冒出来的
Where did he come from?
-要杀了他吗  -我也不知道
- Should we shoot him? - Maybe. I don't know.
你还真他妈够丑的啊
You are one ugly son of a bitch, aren't you?
悠着点
Whoa, man.
我想他应该是饿了
Dude, I think he's hungry.
一定是和别的猿类走散了
He must have gotten separated from the others.
你迷路了吗
You lost?
要回家吗
Trying to get home?
滚吧  离开这里  蠢猴子
Go on! Get out of here, stupid monkey!
快滚  照他说的做  快滚
Go on. You heard him. Go!
那些枪足够杀死所有的猿类了
Enough guns here to kill every ape.
必须警告凯撒
Must warn Caesar.
天知道山上那些人在搞什么鬼
Who knows what humans are really doing up there?
堵住了  得炸开
We gotta clear this blockage.
我不知道你曾有个女儿
I didn't know you had a daughter.
是的
Yeah.
她叫什么
What was her name?
莎拉
Sarah.
我很遗憾
I'm really sorry.
现在有你和你父亲陪着我  所以
Well, now I have you and your dad, so...
没错
Yeah.
-好了  -布置妥当了吗
- All right. - You got all that straight?
引线就那么长了
That's all the wire we got.
注意安全
Brace yourselves.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
-爸爸  -马尔科姆
- Dad! - Malcolm!
马尔科姆  马尔科姆
Malcolm! Malcolm!
爸爸
Dad?
我看不到卡弗
I can't see Carver.
轻点
Don't!
-扶好了  -好的
- Leave it there. - I got it.
骨头没断
It's not broken.
松开  好的
Let go. Good.
谢谢
Thank you.
你救了我们的命
You saved our lives.
我们得把那一大堆碎石给清理掉
We've got a lot of debris to clear now.
可能会耽搁久一点
We might need a bit more time.
多久
How long?
你好呀  小朋友
Hey, buddy.
干什么呢  弄好了吗
What are you doing? Are you finished?
看什么看
What are you looking at?
从箱子里滚出去
Hey, get out of there!
-老子杀了你  -卡弗  你干什么
- Hey! I'll kill you! - Carver, what're you doing?
不要  不要
Don't! Don't!
凯撒  不
Caesar, no!
不要
No.
说过不准带枪
Said no guns!
-不  别这样  -拜托
- No, don't. - Please.
我并不知情
I didn't know.
人类  现在就走
Human leave now!
这下完蛋了
Man, we screwed now.
马尔科姆
Malcolm?
马尔科姆  你要去哪儿
Malcolm, where are you going?
马尔科姆
Malcolm.
拜托  拜托  我得和他谈谈
Please, please, I just need to speak to him.
抱歉  都是我的错  我会让他离开的
I'm sorry. That was all my fault. But I will make him leave.
这是我的家
This my home.
你不该上这来
You should not be here.
我知道
I understand.
马尔科姆
Malcolm.
她病了
She's sick.
她这样多久了
How long has she been this way?
我带了药
I have medicine.
抗生素
Antibiotics.
也许她能帮上忙
Maybe she can help.
不信你
Do not trust you.
我能理解
I don't blame you.
但请相信我
But believe me.
我们并不都像他那样
We are not all like him.
拜托  让我们帮你吧
Please, let us help you.
一天
One day.
你们只能待一天
You stay one day.
父亲  不行
Father, no!
-我们需要更多的时间  -就一天
- We might need more time. - One day!
猿族会提供帮助
Ape will help.
我才不帮忙呢
I will not help!
-你们疯了吧  -把他带走
- This is bullshit, man! - Get him out of here.
走  够了  过来  离开这里
Move! That's enough. Come on, get out of here.
走吧  伙计
Come on, man.
行了吧
Okay?
给我过来
Move, come on!
上去
Get in!
明天见  混蛋
See you tomorrow, asshole.
刚从城市回来  人类十分危险
Just came from the city. Humans very dangerous!
凯撒在哪儿
Where is Caesar?
和人类在一起
With the humans.
亚历克斯
Yo, Alex.
这个继电器坏了  另外找一个来
This relay's busted. See if there's another one.
好
Yeah.
凯撒
Caesar.
不  不  不  别
No! No, no, no, don't!
不  不  不
No! No! No!
凯撒在哪儿  我要见他
Where Caesar? Want Caesar.
凯撒
Caesar!
人类攻击了你的子民
Humans attack your sons.
你还让他们留下
You let them stay!
置猿族于危险之中
Put apes in danger!
凯撒爱护人类却不顾猿族
Caesar love humans more than apes!
不顾你的子民
More than your sons.
猿族
Ape...
不
Not...
杀
Kill...
同类
Ape.
原谅我
Forgive me.
你是我的孩子
You are my son.
我要你听我说
I need you to listen.
你怎么不告诉凯撒人类试枪的事
You didn't tell Caesar about the guns we found?
你也不准说
Neither will you.
你父亲不再信任我了
Your father doesn't trust me now.
你得保护他
You need to protect him.
他对人类的爱让他变得盲目
His love for humans makes him blind.
我知道
I know.
只要人类还在这里
As long as they are here,
我就为凯撒的性命担忧
I fear for Caesar's life.
昨天的事谢谢了
For yesterday.
看  看这儿
Look. Look.
看这儿
Watch.
这里
那是一个星期五
"It was Friday."
一个美妙的下午
"A real nice afternoon."
温暖
"Warm."
我们外出
"We were hanging..."
我们外出郊游
"We were hanging out...
在水潭边上开了一场啤酒聚会
"At this kegger down at the swimming hole."
外出郊游
Hanging out.
游玩
Hanging.
这里  你识字吗
Here. You can read?
这可是好东西
Now, this is the good stuff.
-干杯  -干杯
- Cheers. - Cheers.
你到底有什么毛病
What the hell is wrong with you?
不是让你滚回家吗
I thought we told you to go home!
不
No!
不  走开
No! Go!
-他倒知道这个  -是啊
- He understood that, didn't he? - Yeah.
他好像喜欢你
I think he likes you.
得了吧
Shut up.
好吧  好吧
All right, all right.
想喝一杯吗  丑八怪
You want a drink, fugly?
来  给他点
Go on, give him some.
给他点呀  伙计  看他什么反应
Give him some, man. See what happens.
给你
There you go.
我靠
Shit!
好喝吧
That's good, huh?
好了  好了
Okay. All right.
别激动
Easy.
是的
Yeah.
-别激动  -别激动
- Easy. - Easy.
好的
All right...
马尔科姆
Malcolm!
怎么了  发生什么事了
What is it? What happened?
能用了
It worked.
至少在这里能用了
At least here it did.
城市那边要等回去了才知道
We'll know when we get back to the city.
信任
Trust.
妈的
Son of a bitch.
真他妈能干
You son of a bitch!
灯光
The... lights.
好些了吗
Feeling better?
母亲
Mother...?
人类的枪
Human gun!
快逃
Run.
人类杀了凯撒
Humans kill Caesar!
烧了猿族的家园
Burn ape home!
上  抓住他们
Go! Get them!
猿族必须攻击人类城市
Apes must attack human city!
回击
Fight back!
来啊  为凯撒而战
Come, fight for Caesar!
母猿和孩子留在这里
Females and young stay in woods
我们进城
we go to the city!
我们会为你父亲报仇的
We will avenge your father's death!
埃莉  埃莉
Ellie! Ellie.
这里是旧金山发报点
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到这条信息
If anyone is receiving this message
请报上姓名和所在地  完毕
we ask that you identify yourself and your location. Over.
上  上
Move, move!
如果你收到这条信息
If you are receiving this signal,
请报上所在地  完毕
please state your location. Over.
重复  这里是旧金山发报点
Repeat. This is San Francisco attempting to establish contact.
如果你收到这条信息
If you are receiving this signal
请报上姓名和所在地  完毕
please state your identity and your location. Over.
出什么事了
What is it?
猿类袭击了武器库
The apes attacked the armory, sir.
拉响警报  拉响警报
Sound the alarm! Sound the alarm!
别让它们上墙  别让它们上墙
Keep them off the walls! Keep them off the walls!
快  各就各位
Let's go! Get into position.
-准备好了吗  -好了  长官
- You ready? - Yes, sir.
很好
Good.
听我说
Listen to me.
我们是幸存者
We are survivors!
虽然它们可能拿到了我们的一些武器
Now, they may have got their hands on some of our guns
但它们终究不是人类
but that does not make them men.
它们是动物
They are animals!
我们将击退它们
We will push them back!
干掉他们
Drive them down!
它们别想进来
And they will not get through these doors!
那边  加利福尼亚街
There! California street!
把火箭筒拿来
Bring me the rocket launcher!
我们的所在地有烽火标志
We have a beacon marking our location.
我们需要援助  我们遭到了袭击
Please, we need help. We are under attack.
旧金山  重复
San Francisco. Repeat.
喂
Hello?
收到吗
Do you copy?
人类跑了  抓住他们
Humans escaping! Capture them!
我们肯定快到了
We must be getting close.
我好像看到了  在这下面
I think I see it. It's down here!
爸
Dad!
天啊  马尔科姆
Oh, my God. Malcolm!
埃莉  帮我一把
Ellie, help me.
我的
My...
儿子
son...
我的
My...
家人
family...
在哪
Where?
我不知道
I don't know.
别说话了  你需要休息
Try not to speak. You need to rest.
按住
Hold.
他失血过多
He's lost a lot of blood.
他能挺过去吗
Is he going to make it?
我不明白
I don't understand.
卡弗是从哪弄来的枪
Where did Carver get the gun?
他为什么要这么做
Why would he do this?
猿族
Ape...
什么
What?
这是
Ape...
猿族
did...
干的
this.
上车
Get in the truck.
人类跑到这来了  到处躲藏
Followed the humans here. Hiding everywhere!
我们必须把他们都抓住
We must catch them all!
杀了他
Kill him.
不  不  不
No, no, no.
动手啊  灰灰
Go ahead, Ash.
让人类付出代价
Make humans pay.
凯撒不会希望我们这么做的
Caesar wouldn't want this.
凯撒已经死了
Caesar gone.
猿族现在
Apes follow
听科巴的
Koba now.
天啊  看  聚居地着火了
Oh, my God. Look, the colony's on fire.
我们接下来去哪
Where are we going to go?
凯撒  怎么了
Caesar, what?
是这里吗  快到了吗
Is this it? Are we close?
他要带我们去哪
Where is he taking us?
马尔科姆  停车
Malcolm, stop!
我不明白  我们来这干什么
I don't understand. What are we doing here?
无所谓了
It doesn't matter.
在我们搞清楚家里发生什么事前
We just need a place to hide him
得先找个地方把他藏起来
until we find out what's going on at home.
把桌子挪一下
Go move the table.
好了  就这吧
Okay. Right here.
好了
Okay.
爸  看
Dad, look.
看
Look.
我们得做手术  但我没有工具
We need to operate. I don't have anything.
家里有手术箱  但那...
There's a surgical kit back at the place, but that's...
我去拿
I'll go.
那里不安全
It's not safe.
他是唯一能阻止这一切的人
He's the only one that can stop this.
人类
Humans!
你们现在是猿族的囚犯了
You ape prisoner now!
你们将尝尝生活在笼子里的滋味
You will know life in cage.
外面还有人类
More humans out there.
去  找到他们
Go! Find them!
莫里斯
Maurice...?
科巴说
Koba said
我们太忠于你父亲了
we're too loyal to your father.
保护好自己
Protect yourself.
该死
Shit!
等一下
Hey, wait.
你父亲
Your father.
他还活着
He's alive.
我拿到了
I got it.
他怎么样了
How is he?
你母亲
Your...mother.
弟弟
Brother.
都安全吗
Safe?
暂时安全
For now.
不
No.
不是人类干的
Not human.
是科巴
Koba.
马尔科姆
Malcolm.
开始吧
Yeah.
凯撒
Caesar.
我们得马上开始了
We need to do this now.
儿子
Son.
他怎么样了
How is he?
等等看吧
We'll see.
他很坚强
He's very strong.
不会有事的
It's gonna be okay.
我为这一切
I'm so sorry
向你道歉
for everything.
不
No.
这
I...
都是我的错
am to blame.
但是科巴背叛了你
But Koba betrayed you.
我
I...
选择了相信他
chose to trust him
因为他是猿族
because he is ape.
我一直认为
I always think
猿族比人类善良
ape better than human.
我现在明白了
I see now
我们有多么像人类
how much like them we are.
科巴现在在哪
Where Koba now?
在人类的塔上
On the human tower.
周围有很多拥护者
Loyal apes around him.
那些不愿跟随他的人呢
And those who not follow?
都成了阶下囚
Prisoners.
莫里斯
Maurice.
火箭
Rocket.
科巴杀了灰灰
Koba killed Ash.
其他人也因为恐惧而服从了
Fear makes others follow.
但他们一旦看到你还活着
But when they see you alive
就不会再追随科巴了
they will turn from Koba.
我这么虚弱可不行
Not if I am weak.
猿族只会追随最强者
Ape always seek strongest branch.
我必须想办法阻止他
I must do something to stop him.
父亲
Father.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
求求你们  放我们出去
Please, let us out of here!
好
Okay.
凯撒  看
Caesar, look.
苹果
Apple.
很好
Good.
家
Home.
没错
Yes.
这是你的家
This is your home.
你的家
Your home.
很好  很好
Good. Good.
非常好
That's good.
对不起
Sorry.
我无意打扰
I didn't mean to intrude.
已经两天了
It's been two days.
你儿子还没回来吗
Your son is not back yet?
那是谁
Who was that?
录像里那个
On the video.
是个好人
A good man.
像你一样
Like you.
他们必须偷偷上塔
They need to get to the tower without being seen.
我带他走地下通道
I'm gonna take him through the subway.
我爱你
I love you.
科巴派人去接妇孺了
Koba sent for the females and young.
他们在来的路上了
They're on their way.
母亲也会来
Mother too.
必须马上走了
Must go. Now!
你没事吧
Are you okay?
是谁
Who's there?
是人类就出声
If you're human, you better say so!
是我  我是马尔科姆
It's me! It's Malcolm!
别开枪
Don't shoot!
从楼梯上去
Take the stairs.
就能绕到街上去了
They'll bring you around and up under the street, okay?
去吧
Go.
谢谢
Thank you.
信任
Trust.
好了  我要出来了
All right, I'm coming out!
别开枪
Don't shoot!
看我找到谁了
Look who I found.
我都不知道你是否还活着
I didn't know if you'd made it out.
见到你真好
Good to see you.
别担心
Don't worry.
我们会扭转局面
We're gonna turn all this around.
什么意思  你们在干什么
What do you mean? What's going on?
猿类占领了塔楼
The apes. They're all over the tower.
信号丢失了  没信号了
I lost the signal. It dropped out.
继续试
Keep trying.
马尔科姆  看这个
Malcolm, look at this.
C-4炸弹  每个五磅多
C-4. Five-pound blocks.
我们刚刚开始设置
We just started setting them.
这些炸弹将会炸跨整座塔楼
They're gonna take down the whole tower.
一下把他们全炸死
Blast them all at once.
你正好可以帮上忙
We could use your help.
这里是旧金山
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到
If anyone is receiving this
请报上姓名和所在地  完毕
we ask that you identify yourself and your location. Over.
给  快点
Here. Come on.
如果有人收到  请报上姓名
If anyone is receiving this, we ask that you identify yourself
和所在地  完毕
and your location. Over.
这里是旧金山
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到
If anyone is receiving this...
请报上姓名和所在地
we ask that you identify yourself and your location.
如果有人收到  请报上姓名
If anyone is receiving this, we ask that you identify yourself...
和所在地  完毕
and your location. Over.
德雷福斯
Dreyfus.
-有人听到吗  -维尔纳
- Can anybody hear me? - Werner.
对不起  但我不能让你们这么做
I'm sorry, but I can't let you do this.
我们必须给他个机会
We need to give him a chance.
我们得给他点时间
We need to give him some time.
他现在已经上去了
He's up there right now.
谁上去了
Who's up there?
这里现在没凯撒的位置
Caesar has no place here.
猿族现在
Apes follow
追随科巴
Koba now.
Follow Koba
将引发战争
to war.
猿族将赢得战争
Apes win war!
猿族团结起来力量大
Apes together strong!
凯撒
Caesar...
弱
weak.
科巴更弱
Koba weaker.
你他妈疯了吗
Are you out of your fucking mind?
不  我见过他们的生活
No, I've seen things. I've seen the way they are.
他们的目标跟我们一样  只想求生存
They want what we want, to survive.
他们不想要战争
They don't want a war.
他们是动物
They're animals!
它们袭击了我们
They attacked us!
因为他们以为我们袭击在先
Because they thought we attacked them.
他们以为他死了  但他没有
They think that he's dead, but he's not...
坐下  芬尼
Sit down, Finney!
坐下
Sit down!
我曾信任科巴如同兄弟
Trusted Koba like brother.
凯撒只把人类当兄弟
Caesar brother to human!
科巴为猿族而战
Koba fight for ape!
解放猿族
Free ape!
是杀害猿族
Kill ape.
科巴是为自己而战
Koba fight for Koba.
科巴
Koba
就该待在笼子里
belong in cage.
我知道这听上去很疯狂
I know how this must sound.
我觉得你没明白
I don't think you have any...
你以为阻止我就有用了吗
Do you think stopping me will matter?
他们要来了
They're coming.
我们联系上了北部的一个军事基地
Now, we made contact with a military base up north.
他们已经在路上了
They're already on their way!
是真的
It's true.
德雷福斯
Dreyfus!
你要干什么  伙计
What are you doing, man?
我要拯救人类
I'm saving the human race.
不
No!
猿族
Ape
不杀
not kill...
同类
ape.
你
You are...
不是猿类
not ape.
不
No!
放开他
Leave him!
你们在这不安全
You're not safe here.
他们建立了联系  士兵要来了
They made contact. Other people are coming. Soldiers.
你们得马上离开  所有人
You have to leave now. Everyone.
凯撒  如果你们不走  战争将全面展开
Caesar if you don't go, it'll be all-out war.
战争
War
已经
has already
开始了
begun.
猿族挑起了战争
Ape started war.
人类
And human...
人类不会宽恕
human will not forgive.
在战争开始前
You must go
你必须赶紧离开
before fighting begins.
对不起
I am sorry
朋友
my friend.
我还以为我们有机会
I thought we had a chance.
我也是
I did, too.